בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is קמ"ב kuf mem bet
and we pick up on the last line, we'll pick up on
the last line of קמ"א ע"ב. kuf mem aleph amud bet. The
משנה Mishna spoke about picking up a someone's son, someone could pick
up his son if the son is holding on to a stone
or move a basket that had a stone in it or carry
תרומה טמאה terumah temeiah with תרומה טהורה. terumah tehorah. The implication of
the משנה Mishna is that that מוקצה muktzah can be moved if
it is being somehow moved together as one unit with other things.
And that is different I should mention than טלטול מן הצד. tiltul
min hatzad. טלטול מן הצד tiltul min hatzad is the example I
gave yesterday is I'm going for my book and I knock my
wallet out of the way so I can reach my book. That's
like a one-time motion that pushes it out of the way so
I can get to the thing I'm going for. Here it's an
ongoing moving and carrying but it just happens to be and even
though you're primarily moving the thing that's מותר, mutar, the thing that
is מוקצה muktzah is also part of it. There's a stone in
the kid's hand, there's a stone in the basket and so on.
And the משנה Mishna indicates that it's okay. The גמרא Gemara as
we're going to see, most of the גמרא Gemara of today's דף
daf or the first עמוד amud is basically going to assume that
it's fundamentally not okay and is going to have a way of
redefining what's going on in the משנה. Mishna. Part of that has
to do with the next משנה Mishna we're going to read which
we'll see, but part of it has to do and this is
what we left off with yesterday with רבא's Rava statement because רבא
Rava says that if you carry an infant with a wallet, a
money pouch around its neck out in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, you're
exempt from the infant but you're חייב chayav for the money pouch
because the money pouch is not considered to be secondary to the
infant. It's not like clothing or it's not like a chair or
a bed that the person is on. Therefore since it's not secondary
you are חייב chayav for carrying. And the גמרא Gemara assumes that
the same parameters that apply to the issue of carrying would apply
to the issue of moving מוקצה muktzah and therefore it doesn't understand
why you can move the basket, the kid with the stone in
his hand because why isn't that also considered moving the stone the
same way it would be considered carrying the stone assuming that those
are the same issue. So based on that approach it's going to
lead to a whole rereading of our משנה Mishna and significant limiting
of the cases of the משנה. Mishna. So let's pick up with
that from the bottom of קמ"א ע"ב. kuf mem aleph amud bet.
תנן, Tnan, end of the second line from the bottom. נוטל אדם
את בנו ואבן בידו, notel adam et bno ve-even be-yado, you can
pick up your son with the stone in his hand. So and
how does that fit with רבא Rava who said that were you
to carry you'd be חייב chayav for carrying the stone? So it
should be like a separate act of moving the stone. So אמרי
דבי רבי ינאי, amrei devei Rabbi Yannai, the house of רבי ינאי
Rabbi Yannai they explain, בתינוק שיש לו געגועין על אביו. betinok she-yesh
lo ga'agu'in al aviv. You're right, technically it's a problem, it is
a moving of מוקצה, muktzah, but we allow it because this is
an infant that has particular longing, yearning for his father, the father
has to pick him up or he's going to get himself
sick into a whole fit. I know but it means that there'll
be a particular like emotionally difficult and therefore it's allowed, presumably if
he has to if he's told to drop the stone he'll also
have a crying fit of some nature. So it becomes like רש"י
Rashi says an almost type of a חולה, choleh, not really a
חולה choleh that we allow it. So it's a special allowance. Obviously
that is a very forced read in the משנה. Mishna. So the
גמרא Gemara says אי הכי i hachi if that's true top of
קמ"ב ע"א. kuf mem bet amud aleph. מאי איריא אבן אפילו דינר
נמי? mai irya even afilu dinar nami? Why only a stone? Even
a דינר dinar you should be allowed to pick up your kid
if he's holding on to a דינר. dinar. אלמא אמר רבא לא
שנו אלא אבן אבל דינר אסור. al-ma amar Rava lo shanu ela
even aval dinar assur. Why does רבא Rava himself say it's only
by a stone but a דינר dinar is אסור? assur? Now that
is a legitimate question whatever the explanation of the משנה Mishna is.
If it's about moving, if it's not considered moving מוקצה, muktzah, stone
or דינר dinar shouldn't matter.
Similarly if it is considered moving מוקצה muktzah but it's a special
allowance because the kid is in an emotional state then there should
not be a difference between a דינר dinar or a stone. So
really this question is regardless what is the basis for רבא's Rava
distinction here between a דינר dinar or a stone? So the גמרא
Gemara says like
this: אבן אי נפל לא אתי אבויה לאתויי even ee nafal lo
ati avuye le-atuyei because here's the difference: if the kid drops the
stone he's not going to pick it up. דינר dinar however if
he drops the coin, אי נפל אתי אבויה לאתויי ee nafal ati
avuye le-atuyei the father will come to pick it up. So therefore
the real problem here
is we allow it but we don't allow it in a case
where it could lead to direct moving of the מוקצה. muktzah.
So therefore in the case of the דינר dinar where we're afraid
he drops the דינר dinar you'll pick up the דינר dinar and
therefore it's funny, it's like a גזרה gezeirah on מוקצה muktzah but
that much we won't allow it. And that's the difference between the
stone and the דינר. dinar.
Really anything that's valuable you'd pick up.
Yeah, exactly. תניא כוותיה דרבא, tanya kevateih de-Rava, now we taught like
רבא. Rava. The focus is not on this coin-stone difference which רבא
Rava himself introduced, it's on the issue about whether it's considered to
be moving the stone and whether it's only allowed in this special
case. We taught like רבא: Rava: המוציא כלים מקופלים ומונחים על כתיפו,
hamotzi kelim mekuphalim u-munachim al ketefo, now this is going back to
the issue... of carrying, not moving מוקצה. muktzeh. If somebody takes outside
from his house his garments folded up and on his shoulder, not
wearing them, וסנדליו וטבעותיו בידו v'sandalav v'tab'otav b'yado and carrying and holding
onto his sandals and his rings in his hand, not on his
hand, חייב chayav then you're חייב chayav because you're not wearing your
clothing, you're carrying them. ואם היו מלובש בהן v'im hayu melubash ba-hen
if you were wearing these things פטור patur you'd be exempt. המוציא
אדם וכלים עליו וסנדלו ברגליו וטבעתו בידו ha-motzi adam v'keilav alav v'sandalo
b'raglav v'tab'ato b'yado
if somebody takes out a person, carries out a person and the
person is wearing his clothes and his sandals are on his feet
and his rings are on his hands so here it doesn't mean
in his hand but on his hand. Rashi points out it's funny
because in both cases it says טבעתו בידו tab'ato b'yado
but here it's juxtaposed to סנדלו ברגלו sandalo b'raglo so it's clear
that it means the rings are on his fingers, not in his
hand. Rashi also points out that here it's in the plural טבעותיו
בידיו tab'otav b'yadav
so somehow that more suggests his fingers or anyway they're on his
hand, he's wearing his clothes פטור patur you're exempt. You're exempt for
the person and you're exempt because it's חי נושא את עצמו chai
nosei et atzmo and you're exempt for the clothes because the clothes,
yeah, whatever, that's a separate discussion and you're exempt for the clothes
because the clothes are secondary to the person. ואילו הוציאן כמות שהן
v'ilu hotzian k'mot she-hen and this is the direct support of רבא,
Rava, however if the person was holding his clothes, not wearing his
clothes and you carried the person חייב chayav you would be חייב.
chayav. So you see it is not that anything that a person
is holding onto is considered secondary to the person, it's only things
that in functionally are really טפל tafel you know secondary to to
that person. So the clothes that a person is wearing or the
chair a person is sitting on but if something the person is
something is holding then it's independent of you, you're just holding onto
it and therefore if somebody is carried holding onto something you're exempt
on the live person but you're חייב chayav for the thing that
that person was carrying because that is not considered to be just
a part of that person the live person that you are carrying.
So that supports רבא Rava in terms of the principle of carrying
but then the גמרא Gemara that insists that the same rules would
apply to the question of moving for מוקצה muktzeh which is very
bizarre. I mean מוקצה muktzeh has its own rules. Right? You can
do טלטול בגופו tiltul b'gufo we learned the other day. You can
move מוקצה muktzeh with your body, rolling in מוקצה muktzeh you know
if it's the hay on the bed. You can't you can't go
ahead and carry on your body, right? So obviously there are different
rules for moving מוקצה muktzeh and carrying but the גמרא Gemara assumes
that they're the same and therefore makes our משנה mishna a special
case and it will continue in that vein making every case in
our משנה mishna a special case. Let's take a look. כלכלה והאבן
בתוכה. kalkalah v'ha-even b'tochah. So you have a basket and a stone
inside of it. According to the משנה mishna move the basket, no
problem. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with that. Maybe there's
other stuff in the basket as well so at least you're moving
you know מוקצה muktzeh with other stuff but anyway according to the
משנה mishna no problem. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara does.
ואמאי v'amai why is this true? והוי כלכלה בסיס לדבר האסור. ve-havei
kalkalah basis l'davar ha-asur. Before you get to the fact that you're
moving the stone, the fact that the stone is supported in the
basket that makes the basket a בסיס basis a base and the
basket becomes מוקצה muktzeh just like the stone if it was that
way when שבת Shabbat began. So אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן Amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan so you
could have said it it happened later, it didn't happen when שבת
Shabbat began. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן הכא בכלכלה מלאה פירות עסקינן. Amar Rabba
bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan hacha b'kalkalah m'lei'ah peirot askinan. It
doesn't only have a stone in it, it has a stone and
fruit. And therefore it's not a בסיס basis because something that's a
בסיס לדבר האסור ודבר המותר basis l'davar ha-asur v'davar ha-mutar not only
for דבר האסור davar ha-asur does not have the status of a
בסיס. basis. That's why some people have the practice like of putting
חלה challah on the where you know the on the tray where
the candles are so the candle tray itself doesn't become a בסיס
basis and so on. Anyway that's the basic הלכה. halacha. So therefore
also let's say that you've got your drawer that has מוקצה muktzeh
in it, is it a בסיס basis because it also has clothes
in it and so on. So only if it's solely a בסיס
basis for a דבר האסור. davar ha-asur. Now by also putting saying
that there are fruit there's fruit in the basket, it makes the
case in the משנה mishna better because now like the issue of
the sun, now you are actually moving the fruit. Meaning you know
if you're moving a basket and has a stone in it, it's
harder to claim I'm just moving the basket, the stone happens to
be in it because you focus on what's in the basket. But
if there's fruit and a stone in the basket, then you could
say I'm primarily moving the fruit like I'm primarily picking up my
kid. So we should be happy. But then the גמרא Gemara has
just gotten through saying they're not happy, that they don't believe that
although the משנה mishna seems to say it's okay based on רבא
Rava that actually is not acceptable, that's considered like you are directly
moving the stone. So even if there's fruit in it, one minute
the גמרא's Gemara gonna have a problem. Although it should make it
better, the גמרא Gemara still has a problem. Let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says, I don't get why it's allowed, there's
ways to move the fruit regardless. ולשדינהו לפירי ולשדייה לאבן v'lishdinhu l'peirei
v'lishdyeih l'even
why don't you just empty out the basket, throw out the fruit
with the stone ונינקטינהו בידיה v'ninktinhu b'yadeih
and then pick up the fruit and put the fruit back in
the basket? So you you don't have to carry the stone, there's
a way to avoid it and therefore you should not be allowed.
Again the גמרא Gemara assuming fundamentally this is a problem like fundamentally
the stone and the kid had been a problem and it should
only be allowed under special cases. So here the גמרא Gemara assumes
if you have any other option you should not be allowed to
do it. So the גמרא's Gemara answer is כדרבי אלעאי אמר רב
k'de-Rabbi Ilai amar Rav like רבי אלעאי אמר רב Rabbi Ilai amar
Rav we'll say in a minute by the next case of the
משנה mishna בפירות המיטנפין. b'peirot ha-mitnapin.
So we're talking about
So he says that in the next case of the משנה, Mishna,
here too בפירות המתנפנים, b'peiros hamitnapnim, it's fruit that can easily become
soiled and therefore that is not a solution to say just empty
it all out. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but ולירנהו ניורי,
v'liernahu niurei, so I still don't get it, still like shake it
out, what רש"י Rashi sort of says that means is to like
try to shake the basket to free off the stone and then
just turn it and then just like then just turn it over
so that you know maybe hold on to the fruit or whatever,
but just do away that the stone comes out without the rest
of the fruit. Okay, it's not always possible.
Anyway, which is what the גמרא Gemara will say. Well, actually not,
the גמרא Gemara could have said that's not possible, but let's see
what the גמרא Gemara does answer. אמר רב חייא בר אשי אמר
רב הכא בכלכלה פחותה עסקינן, Amar Rav Chiya bar Ashi Amar Rav
hacha b'kalkala p'chuta askinan, we're actually dealing with a basket that is
that has a hole in it, דאבן גופא נעשית דופן לכלכלה, d'even
gufa na'asis dofen l'kalkala, and the stone actually is filling up the
hole of the basket and therefore it's allowed. Now again, it's crazy
because what is it saying? It's saying that it's really you're not
carrying it as a stone, the stone actually now is a כלי
kli and is part of the basket. You don't need so what's
the whole point of the משנה? Mishna? Right, now you could say
what it means is not exactly that you designated it as as
part of the basket and you made it a כלי, kli, but
that functionally it's preventing the fruit from falling out. And since functionally
it's doing that, the if we if our approach to say to
you is, you know, if you can avoid the stone you have
to, you have to try carrying it without the stone, well there's
no way to do that right now because if I were to
get rid of the stone then all the fruit would fall out
of the basket. Okay, so but the upshot is is that as
opposed to the משנה Mishna which says no problem, the גמרא Gemara
says yes problem, and the only way it's going to be allowed
in the first case is if the kid is having a fit
or whatever emotionally needs you and in the second case it's only
allowed if there's no way to get rid of the stone. Okay,
but under other cases you really have to not do what the
משנה Mishna says you can do. Michael and Charlie.
So I just had two questions on that. So one is then
you don't really need the basket to be filled with anything, right?
If this is functionally part of the basket?
Yeah, but again maybe. And I think תוספות Tosafos says you could
have the גמרא Gemara could have said אלא ela at the end.
Okay, but it but it depends if you're saying the stone is
becoming a כלי kli or you're just saying it happens to be
filling a hole.
So this is my second question, this is what I really wanted
to ask, is based on all this then there really is we
have to be more מחמיר, machmir, right, with the בסיס לדבר האסור
והמותר? basis l'davar ha'asur v'hamutar? You should try to shake the דבר
מותר davar mutar off and then carry it separately if you can?
Yeah, so your חלה challah tray, your candelabrum with your חלה challah
thing, then it really doesn't work, right, because you
can always take the חלה challah off? I know. I know. So
so we are going to no, there's two issues. One is making
the thing a non-בסיס, basis, so the thing itself isn't מוקצה muktza
per se. Then the question is even if the thing it's on
isn't a בסיס, basis, can you pick up pick up the thing
if you're moving the מוקצה muktza that's on it? Fine, and that's
exactly true. From our approach of the גמרא, Gemara, it is very
much limiting or it's saying that you have to do it only
when there's no other option. That is essentially what the גמרא Gemara
is saying and it's limiting the blanket allowance of the משנה. Mishna.
And we will continue in that vein. So hold off. Yeah, go
ahead.
Why is it permitted to deliberately throw the stone out of the
basket? That wouldn't that be just as bad as carrying the stone?
Yeah, so what's not clear, you know, רש"י Rashi says oh להשליך.
l'hashlich. I
it's hard to imagine it means pick up the stone and throw
it, then you're directly moving מוקצה. muktza. I assume it means a
way to that like tip the basket so the stone falls out
so there's some degree of indirection. But yeah, it's pretty funny that
the גמרא Gemara is suggesting that because at least but anyway. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, מטלטלין תרומה. metaltlin terumah.
So that was how we explained the case of the stone in
the basket that somehow there was no other option to get rid
of it. Now you can move טהורה תרומה tehorah terumah with טמאה
תרומה. teme'ah terumah. So going to be the same question. אמר רב
חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, the same issue that the גמרא Gemara does
not like this blanket allowance. So אמר רב חסדא לא שנו אלא
שטהורה למטה וטמאה למעלה. Amar Rav Chisda lo shanu ela shetehorah lemata
utme'ah lemala. This is only if the טהורה tehorah grain is below
and the טמאה teme'ah grain is above so there's no way to
extract the טהורה tehorah grain and you have no choice but to
carry it all together.
אבל טהורה למעלה וטמאה למטה, aval tehorah lemala utme'ah lemata, but if
it's the reverse and the טהורה tehorah grain is above and the
טמאה teme'ah one is below, שקיל ליה לטהור ושביק ליה לטמא, shakil
lei l'tahor v'shavik lei l'tamai, then just remove the טהורה tehorah grain
and leave the rest behind so you're not allowed to do it
again if you have another option. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכי
טהורה למטה נמי, v'chi tehorah lemata nami, I don't get it, so
the גמרא Gemara why should it be a problem even if the
טהורה tehorah grain is below?
לישדינהו ולנקטינהו, lishdeinhu u'lenkatneinhu, why not just throw it all out and
then just pick up the טהורה tehorah stuff even if it's on
the bottom? So אמר רבי אלעאי אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Ilai Amar
Rav, so this is the where it was originally said and then
it was applied the first time was said to the end of
the משנה, Mishna, we before applied it to the middle of the
משנה. Mishna. בפירות המתנפנים עסקינן, b'peiros hamitnapnim askinan, we're talking about grain
or whatever fruit that will become easily soiled. So if the טמאה
teme'ah stuff טהורה tehorah stuff is below, you have no choice because
there's no way of throwing it out you'll just ruin it. But
if the טהורה tehorah stuff is above, then we're demanding that you
remove the טהורה tehorah stuff. Again, you are not allowed to do
what the משנה Mishna says you can do if you have another
option. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, מיתיבי, Meisivi, I'll ask you
on this: מטלטלין תרומה טמאה עם הטהורה ועם החולין. metaltlin terumah teme'ah
im hatehorah v'im hachullin. We have a ברייתא Braisa that says you
can carry טמאה תרומה teme'ah terumah with טהורה תרומה tehorah terumah which
is edible and therefore not מוקצה muktza or חולין chullin non-תרומה. terumah.
And then it elaborates. Right, that's a... Essentially what our משנה Mishnah.
*Mishnah* says, but the ברייתא Beraisa, *Braita* then elaborates. בין שהטהורה למעלה
וטמאה למטה *Bein shehatahorah lemala utme'ah lemata*, whether the טהורה *tehorah* grain
is above and the טמאה *teme'ah* below, בין שטמאה למעלה והטהורה למטה
*bein sheteme'ah lemala vehatahorah lemata* or the טמאה *teme'ah* grain is above
and the טהורה *tehorah* below. So even if the טהורה *tehorah* grain
is above and there's another option, you should be allowed to do
it. You're allowed to do it. תיופתא דרב חסדא *Tiyufta deRav Chisda*,
that's a contradiction to רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*. אמר לך רב חסדא
*Amar lecha Rav Chisda*, מתניתין לצורך גופו *matnisin letzorech gufo*, ברייתא braita:
לצורך מקומו *braita letzorech mekomo*. In our משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* you wanted
the grain. In our ברייתא braita, *Braita* you only wanted to get
the basket out of the way. Now normally these are distinction between
כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli she'melachto l'issur, *kli shemelachto le'issur*, but that's not
our point here. Our point is the following: If why am I
moving the basket? If the only reason I'm moving the basket is
because I need the place of the basket, then I really don't
have another option. What's my option? You say, oh, just take the
טהורה *tehorah* grain and leave the rest behind. I'm not interested in
the טהורה *tehorah* grain, I'm interested in moving it. So if I'm
interested in moving it, it doesn't matter what's above or what's below.
I need to move the whole thing, right? Because if I just
took the טהורה *tehorah* grain I'd still be left with a basket
with טמאה *teme'ah* grain in it. So when you need to move
the whole thing, you don't have another option. Fine, you can move
it. But when you're only interested in the grain, then if you
can remove the טהורה *tehorah* grain because the טהורה *tehorah* grain is
above, you have to remove the טהורה *tehorah* grain without moving the
whole basket. So again, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* very consistent and it
says what our משנה mishnah *Mishnah* allows, great, if there happens to
be מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh* together with and it's being sort of taken
along with everything else, that's only if you have no other option.
But if you have another option, then you have to just focus
on the non-מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh* and find a way to move that
alone. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. מאי דוחקיה דרב חסדא
לאוקמי מתניתין לצורך גופו *Mai dukhkei deRav Chisda le'ukmei matnisin letzorech gufo*?
Okay, so I get רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*'s point, but why did
he have to say that the משנה mishnah. *Mishnah* was a case
where you needed the grain and then qualify it that it's only
when the טהורה *tehorah* grain is below? Why not just say that
the משנה mishnah *Mishnah*'s a case where you needed to move the
basket and therefore it wouldn't matter what's above and below? Why did
he assume the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* was a case where you needed
the grain? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רבא Amar Rava,
מתניתין כוותיה דייקא *Amar Rava matnisin kevasei dika*, because the משנה mishnah
*Mishnah*, if the close read of the words of the משנה mishnah
*Mishnah* indicate like רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* that the case in the
משנה mishnah. *Mishnah* is where you needed the grain. Why is that?
And therefore you have to distinguish what's above and what's below. Where
do you get that from the משנה mishnah *Mishnah*? דקתני סיפא *Di-ktani
seifa*, because the end of the משנה mishnah *Mishnah*, which really for
us it's the next משנה mishnah: *Mishnah*, we'll see when we turn
the page, מניח meiniach. על הכר *Mani'ach al hakar*, let's say you
left money on your pillow. So מנערת הכר והן נופלות *Mena'eret hakar
vehaynoflot*, you can shake the pillow off and the money will fall
down so that you can use the pillow. It's a type of
again like a טלטול מן הצד tiltul min hatzad. *tiltul min hatzad*
because you're interested in the כר *kar* not in moving the money.
ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי Rebbe, יוחנן *Ve'amar Rabba bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan*, now רבה בר בר חנה *Rabba bar
bar Chana* says in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, לא
שנו אלא לצורך גופו lo shanu ela letzorech gufo, *Lo shanu ela
letzorech gufo*, that's only if you need to use the pillow, then
you can do this. אבל לצורך מקומו Aval l'tzorech mekomo, *Aval letzorech
mekomo*, but if you need the place, then not only if you
need the pillow do you have to do that, but if you
need the place of the pillow, if you shake the money off
then the money is lying right there, the money still is also
in the way. So if you need actually the place of the
pillow, then you don't have to bother with that. מטלטלו ועודן עליו
metaltelo v'odan alav, *Metaltelo ve'odan alav*, you can move it with the
money on it. Okay, so basically what he says, same point: if
you've got מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh* on something and but you're moving the
דבר היתר davar heter *devar heter* and the מוקצה muktzah. *muktzeh*'s being
moved along, if you need to move the whole thing because you
need the place, no problem. So why does our משנה mishnah. *Mishnah*
say shake it off? Because that was a case where that would
have been a solution, that was an acceptable solution. You only needed
to use the pillow, you didn't want to move everything out of
the way. So, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ומידי סיפא לצורך
גופו רישא נמי לצורך גופו *Umi-de-seifa letzorech gufo reisha nami letzorech gufo*,
since the case of the pillow is where you needed
the pillow, רישא *reisha* also where you need the grain. So the
upshot of this again is an assumption, it's not clear in the
משנה mishna *Mishnah*, but an assumption is that this is only allowable
moving non-מוקצה muktzah. *muktzeh* together with מוקצה muktzah. *muktzeh* when they're all
bundled together in some way, it's on it, it's in it, whatever.
The משנה mishna *Mishnah* sounds like it's allowable across the board. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it's only allowable when there's no option. So
if you've got to move the whole thing out of the way,
there's no option, fine. Move the pillow with the money, move the
basket with the grain. But if you're only interested in the thing
itself and you can get to the thing itself, then you can't
move the whole thing. So shake the money off the pillow so
now you can have just the pillow. Take the טהורה *tehorah* grain
from the top of the basket so and that therefore there's no
allowance to move the טמאה *teme'ah* grain together with it.
Yeah, even in the case where you actually need the space of
the pillow which has the money on it and you're allowed to
take the pillow with the money, but let's say you could shake
it off and the money would just roll someplace else, and then
that
would be fine,
is that something you have to do? מנער *Mena'er*? Even when it's
for its place you can take it?
No, I don't think so. I think that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
the basic principle here is, you know, it's when there are no
good alternatives. So if that's a good alternative you'd have to do
that. Okay, yes.
Question about the basket?
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will get to that. About the money
and the pillow, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will get to that. Okay,
רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehudah omer, אף מעלים *Rabbi Yehuda omer af
ma'alim*. Now we're going to get back to this whole מוקצה muktzah
*muktzeh* and do you have alternatives or not and so on in
a minute when we get to the next משנה mishnah. *Mishnah*, but
first we focus on a totally different point at the end of
our משנה mishnah, *Mishnah* because we mentioned the issue of eating
תרומה terumah, *terumah* or תרומה terumah *terumah*. because there's a sense of
like the כהן is losing out because he deserved the תרומה, terumah
you have to separate one unit of the hundred to therefore replace
the תרומה terumah, that got mixed up. Okay, so that's the principle,
that's called to be מעלה, ma'aleh, raise it up once there's דמוע,
dimua, once it's a mixture of תרומה terumah with חולין, chullin, you
raise up if it's one in a hundred and בטל, batel, you
raise up one unit and then it's מותר. mutar.
Because it's just תרומה, terumah right?
Yeah. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that you can do that
on שבת. Shabbos. Now you can't take תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros on
שבת Shabbos because it's like you're fixing the food. So why can
you do this, which essentially is also fixing the food? So let's
take a look. רבי יהודה אומר אף מעלין. Rabbi Yehuda omer af
ma'alin. The גמרא Gemara says ואמאי, ve'amai, why is that allowed? הא
קא מתקן, ha ka metaken, you're fixing the food. רבי יהודה כרבי
אליעזר סבירא ליה. Rabbi Yehuda k'Rabbi Eliezer sevira leh. He's like רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דאמר תרומה בעיני מחיתא. de'amar terumah b'eini machata.
The תרומה terumah is like it's already set aside by itself when
it gets this case of things getting mixed up with grain and
becoming בטל, batel, the unit you have to remove, it's like it's
already been removed. Where do you see this idea? דתנן, de'tnan, we
taught in the משנה. mishnah. סאה תרומה שנפלה לפחות ממאה, se'ah terumah
she'nafla l'pachos mi'me'ah, one unit of תרומה terumah. fell into less than
a hundred units of חולין, chullin, let's say ninety units of חולין.
chullin. ונדמעו, ve'nidme'u, and they all became אסור, asur, דמוע, dimua, דמוע,
dimua, it all became a mixture because it's not
בטל. batel. ונפל מן המדומע למקום אחר, ve'nafal min ha'meduma l'makom acher,
then one unit of this mixture fell into
another basket of חולין. chullin. Okay, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר
מדמעה כתרומה, omer medama'ah k'terumah, you assume the one unit from the
mixture that fell over was 100% תרומה terumah? and now if it's
into another sort of box of grain, you would need a hundred
times the one unit. That's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, ודאי,
vada'i, like it's as if it were definite תרומה. terumah וחכמים אומרים,
ve'Chachamim omrim, the sages say, אין המדומע מדמע אלא לפי חשבון. ein
ha'meduma medama ela lefi cheshbon. The mixture only creates a problematic mixture
according to its proportion, which means if you have one fell into
ninety and it's not בטל, batel, then you take one unit out.
How much of that unit do you assume is
תרומה? terumah. 1/90th. Okay, so therefore if that one unit falls into
just two units, even less, you can do the math, it's בטל
batel because you assume only 1/90th of תרומה terumah. is getting mixed
up into the second mixture. Okay, so that's the rabbis' position, makes
a lot of sense, you assume equal distribution and it's proportional, but
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no, when the one unit comes out
of the mixture, you assume it's 100% תרומה. terumah? What's the logic
of that? So the גמרא Gemara says the logic is is that
he says when you have to remove the unit, it's like it's
been already removed. So any unit that gets taken out, even if
you haven't yet removed it, any unit that gets removed we assume
that was the unit you were going to remove and it's already
been removed and it's full תרומה. terumah So wait a minute, if
he says that, then the גמרא Gemara says maybe we could also
use that as a לקולא le'kula and say it's not a problem
separating it on שבת Shabbos because it's like it's already happened. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, אימור דשמעת ליה לחומרא. eimar de'shamas
leh l'chumra. Wait a minute,
when would he say that idea that it's all considered תרומה? terumah
לחומרא. l'chumra. But לקולא מי שמעת ליה, bat l'kula mi shamas leh,
we never have any indication that he would be lenient based on
this idea, you know, and say that it's you don't have to
separate it or whatever it's not a problem separating it on שבת,
Shabbos, it's like it already took place. We don't know he would
be totally consistent with that position even to be lenient. אלא הוא
דאמר כרבי שמעון. ela hu de'amar k'Rabbi Shimon. He says like רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דתנן, de'tnan, we taught in the משנה. סאה תרומה
שנפלה למאה. se'ah terumah she'nafla l'me'ah. So again, one unit of תרומה
terumah fell into a hundred. Fine, בטל. batel. שלום על ישראל. shalom
al Yisrael. But wait a minute, ולא הספיק להגביה, ve'lo hispik lehagbi'ah,
you didn't get a chance yet to remove the one unit you
were supposed to remove עד שנפלה אחרת, ad she'nafla acheres,
and now a second unit fell in. Okay, so now you have
two units of תרומה terumah mixed up with a hundred, that's not
enough, it's only a 50 to 1 ratio. What's the story? הרי
זו אסורה, harei zo asura, it's forbidden because it's only a 50
to 1 ratio. ורבי שמעון מתיר, ve'Rabbi Shimon matir, רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon allows it. So we assume why does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
allow it? Because we assume according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon as
soon as the first unit fell in, right, it was בטל batel
and it's like the unit that had to be removed was already
removed. So it's like all you have here is pure חולין. chullin.
The one unit of תרומה terumah is like it's already separate so
when the next unit falls in, it's not joining with an existing
unit because wherever that unit is, it's like it's already been removed.
So therefore you see even to be lenient, he says we consider
the unit already removed. So the גמרא Gemara says וממאי, u'mimai, how
makes you say that's the debate? דילמא התם בהא קמיפלגי, dilma hasam
be'ha kamifl'gi, maybe this is the debate. דתנא קמא סבר, de'Tanna Kamma
savar, the first תנא Tanna held, אף על גב דנפלו זה אחר
זה, af al gav de'naflu zeh acher zeh, though they fell one
after the other, כמאן דנפלו בבת אחת דמי, k'man de'naflu b'vas achas
dami, we look at it as if they fell the same time,
so two units into a hundred, not בטל. batel. והא לחמישין נפלה
והא לחמישין נפלה, ve'ha l'chamishin nafla ve'ha l'chamishin nafla, it's like each
one fell into fifty, it's only a fifty to one ratio. ורבי
שמעון סבר, ve'Rabbi Shimon savar, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon held, קמייתא
בטלה במאה, kamaisa batela b'me'ah, the first unit that fell in became
בטל, batel, והא תיבטל במאה וחדא, ve'ha tibatel b'me'ah ve'chada, meaning what
he is saying is he doesn't have to say it's like the
unit was already removed. All he has to say is that the
תרומה terumah was בטל, batel, right? So the first unit of תרומה
terumah that fell in was בטל. batel. When another unit falls in,
it doesn't join with the existing unit, because the existing unit was
already בטל. batel. That's a phrase the גמרא Gemara calls קמא קמא
בטיל. kama kama batel. You know, the first one becomes בטל, batel,
and when the next one falls in, you don't have to worry
about the first one, it was already בטל. batel. So you don't
have to say the unit was already removed because you can say
it's בטל batel and you still have an obligation. The תרומה's terumah
בטל. batel. You can't eat this grain until you remove a unit
of grain. But the תרומה terumah itself is already בטל. batel. So
when the next unit falls in, wait a minute, when the next
unit falls in, it's all falling into all חולין. chullin. Okay, but
that doesn't mean that it's as if you've removed your unit, it
just means that the תרומה terumah is בטל. batel. And that won't
help you for שבת Shabbos where you have to imagine it as
if the grain is already fully fixed. For this case, it doesn't
have to be fully fixed, it just has to be that there's
no longer any תרומה terumah there. And that we're able to say
even before you remove the unit. Now מיגו, migo, you know, do
you say it forever? And the answer is no. You know, once
it gets to a point where the reality contradicts the halachic status,
like there's a רוב rov of the other thing, or it's the
other or it's tasteable, if it's מין באינו מינו, min b'eino mino,
then you don't say קמא קמא בטיל. kama kama batel. But, okay,
at this stage you do. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, there's
a difference between saying the grain is fixed and saying the תרומה
terumah is בטל. batel. אלא הוא דאמר כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Ella,
hu d'amar k'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. Fine, he goes like רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar. דתניא, D'tanya,
and this is a direct statement about שבת Shabbos and separating grain
from דימוע dimua on שבת. Shabbos. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi
Shimon Ben Elazar omer, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar
says, נותן עיניו בצד זה ואוכל מצד אחר. nosen einav b'tzad zeh
v'ochel mitzad acher.
You can look at one side of the pile, meaning if you
have to remove your one unit of grain for this mixture on
שבת, Shabbat, you can sort of in your mind say I will
designate, I'm thinking about the unit over there, you know, in the
southwest corner of this pile, and then ואוכל מצד אחר, v'ochel mitzad
acher. you eat from the rest of the grain. So you don't
actually have to do a physical separation, you just have to have
in mind which is going to be the portion you're going to
use. So if that's all you have to do, then it's really
not, it seems like it's not so problematic to remove it, it's
as if it's already removed because if it's not then considered to
have been already removed, then you wouldn't even be allowed to do
this, it would be like fixing. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי
סבר לה כוותיה? u'mi savar lah k'vosei? Wait a minute, does חזקיה
Chizkiyah hold like him? והא מיפלג פליגי, V'ha miflag paligi, you see
that they argue. דף קמ"ב עמוד ב', Daf kuf mem beis amud
beis,
דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah אומר,
מעלין את המדומה באחד ומאה. ma'alin es hamiduma b'echad u'me'ah.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says you can actually separate the מדומה miduma
if it's בטל batel one in a hundred. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
אומר, Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar omer, נותן עיניו בצד זה nosen einav
b'tzad zeh ואוכל מצד אחר. v'ochel mitzad acher, You can't physically separate
it, but you can mentally designate. So you see that he, so
he might say that that's fine, as long as you're not doing
a physical act, the physical act looks like fixing. So רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda. is not the same as רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi
Shimon Ben Elazar. So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי יהודה אזיל כרבי
שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Yehudah azil k'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, fine, it's
the same general approach, he just takes it one step further. Once
you say that you can just designate it mentally, that means that
it's not really seen as fixing because it doesn't really need to
be separated to be fixed. So if it's not really seen as
fixing, then even if you really do it, it's not really fixing
because it's really not something that really requires the full act of
separation. Okay, so because דימוע dimua can be is a different status
than real תרומות ומעשרות, terumos u'ma'asros, it's only a rabbinic problem, it's
basically already בטל, batel, I think we should reiterate that point, the
תרומה terumah is already בטל, batel, it's just an obligation to separate
a unit, but the תרומה's already בטל, batel, it's not so much
like fixing and therefore according to one approach you can just think
about and the other approach you can actually even physically remove it.
Okay, so now that was an interesting digression about תרומה and שבת,
Shabbos, now we go back to מוקצה muktzah. when you're moving a
דבר היתר heter and you're moving a דבר איסור davar issur with
it. Let's take a look. האבן שעל פי החבית. Ha'even she'al pi
hachavis. If you have a stone on a barrel, מטה לה והיא
נופלת, mataltah v'hi nofeles, tip the barrel over and the stone will
fall off and therefore you can go and get access to the
barrel.
Or maybe you have to carry it, so you tip it off
so that it falls and then you can carry. היתה בין החביות,
ha'yesa bein hachaviyos,
but let's say this barrel was amongst other barrels and you don't
want to tip it because it's going to, well רש"י Rashi says
you don't want to tip it because it'll break the other barrels,
but it could also be you can't tip it because there's no
space to tip. Anyway, מגביה, magbiya, you lift it up, ומטה לה
והיא נופלת, u'mataltah v'hi nofeles, and then you tip it over. So
fine, then you get to a certain you wait till you're in
a circumstance where you can tip it over. Now, מעות
שעל הכר, ma'os she'al hakar, again this is what we quoted before,
money on the pillow, מנער את הכר והן נופלות, m'na'er hakkar v'hen
noflos, you shake it out and they fall off and then you
can use it. היתה עליו לשלשת, Ha'yesa alav lishleshes, if there was
some type of like a stain or something on it, spittle or
some type of a thing, so now we're moving from מוקצה muktzah,
to
ליבון, libbun, cleansing,
מקנחה בסמרטוט, m'kanchesah b'smartut, you can wipe it with a rag. היתה
של עור, Ha'yesa shel or, now that's leather cloth because then you're
just wiping it from the surface as I told
you
if
have... because leather it's all on the surface, it's not ליבון libbun
and therefore you can even use water. Now רש״י Rashi does say
that it would be possible
to actually do כיבוס kibus on what do you call it, if
you took a look at רש״י: Rashi: נותן עליה מים עד שתכלה.
noten aleha mayim ad shetichleh. רש״י Rashi says: ומיהו כיבוס ממש לא
הוי הואיל וסתם כלים בבגדי עור רכים נינהו. umihu kibus mamash lo
havay ho'il ustam kelim bevigdey or rakim ninhu. שייך למימר בהו כיבוס
בעורות רכים. shayach lemeymar behu kibus be'orot rakim.
Oh, the ב beis is wrong. Oh yes, דהואיל וסתם כלים בבגדי
עור רכים נינהו, d'ho'il ustam kelim bevigdey or rakim ninhu, since these
are normally soft, שייך למימר בהו כיבוס בעורות רכים, shayach lemeymar behu
kibus be'orot rakim, it would be possible to talk about it if
it were like, you know, if it were
soft leather. ומיהו שרייתן לאו זהו כיבוסן. umihu sheriyatan lav zehu kibusan.
So רש״י Rashi says actually is that under certain circumstances just putting
water on it is not enough to be considered a כיבוס, kibus,
but under some circumstances actually you could have a problem of כיבוס
kibus by leather. I just want to note that rather
than putting water is the wrong point.
Right, I don't want to go into the details but I just
want to note it because the normal assumption is that you really
don't have a... the גמרא Gemara before talked about a problem of
oil on leather and about treating leather, מעבד. me'abed. Okay, but the
idea of laundering that primarily is an issue much more with cloth
and garments although רש״י Rashi says that there are cases it would
be a concern with leather. Now going back to the מוקצה muktzah.
issue I just want to say that
this משנה seems to be why the גמרא Gemara was limiting the
previous משנה. Because the previous משנה said carry the basket with the
stone, carry the kid with the stone. This משנה sounds like you
have to try to shake the thing off. Okay, so because of
this, this might have been what partly informed the earlier discussion on
the עמוד א׳ amud alef where the גמרא Gemara says it's only
when you have no other choice are you allowed to carry the
whole thing together. Right, where was it getting it? The משנה sounds
like it was a blanket allowance. Well this משנה emphasizing the idea
of shaking it off seems to be the one that says, seems
to be the saying: if you can do it with removing it
then you have to remove it, you cannot carry it with the
thing on. Okay, so seems to be that's presumably... that would be
my best guess why we had all of those qualifications on the
עמוד א׳ amud alef because of what's implied by this משנה. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says although the משנה never explicitly...
even this משנה doesn't really say it but it's at least it's
implied. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב הונא אמר
רב לא שנו אלא בשוכח. amar Rav Huna amar Rav lo shanu
ela beshoche'ach. Now here's the point that Paul raised. One minute, why
isn't the pillow a בסיס? basis? Okay, no, that's when you forgot
the money. אבל במניח, aval bemani'ach, if you intentionally left the money
there, נעשה בסיס לדבר האסור, na'asa basis ledavar ha'asur, then it is
a בסיס, basis, a support, and therefore the thing itself becomes מוקצה.
muktzah So you can't touch it at all. Right. היתה בין החביות.
hayta bein hachaviyot. Now if the barrel was between the other barrels
then you can't tip it so you can move the whole thing
and when you get it to a place you can tip it
you tip it. מאן תנא? man tana? Who is the תנא? tana?
דכל היכא דאיכא איסור והיתר בהיתר
טרחינן באיסור לא טרחינן? d'kol haycha d'ika issur veheter beheter tarchinan be'issur
lo tarchinan? Who is the one that says that whenever there's היתר
heter and איסור issur we focus on the היתר heter and not
on the איסור? issur? Which basically means that we try to get
it...
right רש״י Rashi says the fact that we demand that you lift
up the barrel and tip the barrel rather than directly removing the
stone. Okay now that's a pretty funny question because why do you
have to go looking for parallels? Directly moving the stone is directly
violating מוקצה. muktzah. Fundamentally moving the barrel and tipping the stone off
so you can use the barrel is like טלטול מן הצד. So
but for some strange reason the גמרא Gemara, abstracts this and rather
than saying... right, you understand the point right? To directly move the
stone would be to move מוקצה. muktzah, So move the barrel and
tip, you can say yeah I'm not directly moving it, I'm fundamentally
moving the barrel or whatever. But the גמרא Gemara somehow makes this
an abstract question. We have a choice, you could either focus on
the stone which is easier or the barrel which is harder. We're
going to demand you focus on the barrel, on the היתר heter
not the איסור issur and this is a general principle, focus on
the היתר heter not the איסור. issur. And so where else do
we see this? אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל היא. amar Rabbah bar bar Channah amar Rabbi Yochanan
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel hi. This is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel. דתנן d'tenan we taught in the משנה: הבורר קטנית
ביום טוב, haborer kitnit beyom tov, if you select legumes on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. בית שמאי אומרים בורר אוכל ואוכל. Beit Shammai omrim
borer ochel v'ochel. Now you're allowed to do בורר borer on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. But בית שמאי Beit Shammai doesn't really allow it
so much. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says בורר אוכל ואוכל. borer ochel
v'ochel. You select the food and eat it sort of like how
you do בורר borer on שבת. Shabbos. You focus on the food
and you eat it immediately. ובית הלל אומרים בורר כדרכו. uBeit Hillel
omrim borer kedarko. ובית הלל v'Beit Hillel says בורר כדרכו, borer kedarko,
you can do it the normal way. The normal way of doing
בורר borer usually is that there's you remove the פסולת psolest which
is less, you know, the chaff or the contaminant. So בית הלל
Beit Hillel is much more lenient on יום טוב. Yom Tov. בחיקו
ובתמחוי. becheyko uvetamchui. Not only that, you don't have to just use
your hand, you can put it in your lap and you can
use a vessel like a type of a plate to help you
do it. So בית הלל Beit Hillel is much more lenient on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. דתניא d'tanya we taught in a ברייתא: אמר
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל במה דברים אמורים? amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
bameh devarim amurim? When did בית הלל Beit Hillel say you can
do it the normal way which means remove the פסולת? psolest? שהאוכל
מרובה על
הפסולת. sheha'ochel merubeh al hapsolest. When there's more אוכל ochel than פסולת
psolest and then you remove the פסולת psolest because that's the even
though that's the איסור, issur, the problematic thing, the thing you're not
eating... but nevertheless it's the minority and it's easier. אבל פסולת מרובה
על האוכל, Aval psoiles merubeh al ha'ochel, if the majority is פסולת,
psoiles, דברי הכל בורר אוכל, Divrei hakol borer ochel, you have to
focus on the food because he... the only reason he's saying that
we allow בית הלל Beis Hillel allows you to remove the פסולת
psoiles is because it's easier to remove the פסולת psoiles because there's
less of the פסולת psoiles than there is of the אוכל, ochel,
right? You understand the idea, right? If you've got a pile of
gra- a thing of grapes and a few stones are in it,
you're not going to remove the grapes, you're going to select out
the stone. So therefore we do allow you to focus on the
פסולת psoiles when it is the minority and when it is easier.
And יום טוב Yom Tov and well, it's יום טוב Yom Tov
is what allows בורר. borer. But the גמרא Gemara. is saying is
beyond the בורר borer issue, there's a preference for focusing on the
היתר heter. unless by focusing on the איסור issur it makes your
life easier. So the גמרא Gemara, says okay, but we're back to
square one. Here focusing on the stone would have made my life
easier; I could have picked up the stone and thrown it away.
So I still don't get why I have to pick up the
barrel? So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והכא vehacha in this
case, דכי אוכל מרובה
על הפסולת דמי. dechi ochel merubeh al hapsoiles dami. It's like the
food is greater than the contaminant, because it's easier to focus on
the stone and remove the stone. So I still don't get why
I can't just move the stone. So גמרא Gemara says no. הכא
נמי hacha nami here too, כיון דאיבעי למשקל לא משתקלי יין עד
דשקלי. kivan d'ibaei lemishkal lo mishtaklei yayin ad d'shaklei.
So I'm taking out the word אבן. even. It's a debate of
רש"י תוספות, Rashi Tosafos, but we'll do it without the word אבן.
even. Since if you wanted to get all the wine, you could
not get the wine without picking up the barrel, you can't get
the wine at the bottom of the barrel without picking up the
barrel. So there are cases where you'd have to move the barrel
anyway, this is the way רש"י Rashi is reading it. כפסולת מרובה
על האוכל דמי. Kepsoiles merubeh al ha'ochel dami. It's like the case
where the פסולת psoiles is the majority, which means what? Again, we
want you to focus on the היתר. heter What about the idea
that if it's easier to focus on the איסור issur we'll do
that? Yeah, it is easier to focus on the stone, but nevertheless
because there are many scenarios you'll have to pick up the barrel
anyway, we say just go ahead and pick up the barrel, that's
not a big טרחא, tircha, it would be part of the process
of getting the wine anyway. Okay so that's basically the גמרא's Gemara
answer. Now the problem, as I said, with all of this is
this bizarre assumption that of the similar the גמרא Gemara before was
comparing carrying, what defines carrying as what defines moving. And again it's
strange. Why shouldn't מוקצה muktzah, have its own parameters? We know it
does, but at least there it was somewhat similar. There's a question
of if I move A who's holding on to B, is it
considered like I'm directly moving B or not? You could see the
analogy. Here, it seems quite strange. Right, when I pick off the
stone I'm directly moving מוקצה. muktzah. Who would have a הוה אמינא
hava amina I'm allowed to do that? But if I pick up
the barrel and I'm fundamentally moving היתר heter and the stone happens
to be on it, then and that's a completely different type of
a thing that has nothing to do with this discussion about if
I'm doing בורר borer do I focus on the thing that's easier
or harder or the thing that's היתר heter? or איסור? issur? So
I don't know, it's very strange to me the whole comparison of
the גמרא, Gemara but somehow it makes the comparison and then it
resolves it by saying that here too, there's no this is you
would have to pick up the barrel anyway. I should just point
out that the implication of this is, is if there are cases
where there again is no other option but to directly move the
מוקצה, muktzeh the implication of this גמרא Gemara is that you could
directly move the מוקצה. muktzeh, Okay, we don't say that. Right. Okay,
so again it's a very strange גמרא. Gemara Let's continue. תניא רבי
יוסי אומר היתה חבית מונחת באוצר. Tanya Rabbi Yose omer hayisa chavis
munachas ba'otzar. If the barrel was in the
storehouse, meaning it was surrounded with a lot of other barrels. או
שהיו כלי זכוכית מונחין תחתיה, O shehayu klei zechuchis munachin tachteha, or
there were glass vessels all around it so if you tipped over
the stone you'd break it. In that case, מגביה למקום אחר ומטה
על צדה והיא נופלת, magbi'ah lemakom acher umateh al tzidah vehina nopheles,
you remove it to another place and you tip it over when
you're able, ונוטל הימנו מה שצריך לו, venoteil heimenu mah shetzarich lo,
and you take out the wine you need, ומחזיר למקומו, umachzir limkomo,
and you put it back. So again the principle being though when
you're able to tip it over, you have to tip it over.
And that I believe is what led the גמרא, Gemara I'm repeating
myself, what led the גמרא Gemara. on the עמוד א amud aleph
to limit the entire previous משנה. That when is it allowed when
you're moving the מוקצה muktzeh. with the היתר? heter If you don't
have an option of getting rid of the מוקצה. muktzeh, But if
you have a way of getting rid of the מוקצה, muktzeh then
you gotta get rid of it.
But what you just said before though, if you didn't need the
whole wine in the barrel, you just needed the top and it
would be easier just to move the stone, you didn't need
to do- No, that's what I'm saying, we don't- No. No, we
don't say that. Okay. You have to get rid of the מוקצה,
muktzeh not by directly moving it, you have to get rid of
it by shaking it or whatever other ways of getting rid of
it, we're not saying directly moving it. Okay. מעות על הכר, Ma'os
al hakar, money's on the pillow. אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר
רב, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav, לא שנו אלא בשוכח.
lo shanu ela beshoche'ach. Again, that's only if you forgot the money.
Oh, I'm sorry, before when I said this point about the case
about forgetting, I said it was about the money on the pillow,
but actually it was about the first case. So before the question
is why isn't the barrel a בסיס basis to a stone? And
it said because you forgot the stone on the barrel, you didn't
intentionally put it that way. And here it's asking the same question
about the money on the pillow. לא שנו אלא בשוכח, lo shanu
ela beshoche'ach, that's only when you forgot the money on the pillow,
אבל במניח, aval bemaniach, if you intentionally put it there, נעשה בסיס
לדבר אסור, na'aseh basis ledavar assur, then it's a בסיס basis and
then the pillow itself becomes מוקצה. muktzeh אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, לא
שנו אלא לצורך גופו, lo shanu ela l'tzorech gufo, and this is
also what we said on the עמוד א. amud aleph. The this
fact that we tell you you gotta shake off the money is
only cause you want to use the pillow, so here's a way
of doing it without having to ca- carry the money around, shake
it off. אבל לצורך מקומו, aval l'tzorech mekomo, if you need the
space and you don't want the money in the space either, you
want to get everything out of the way, in that case מטלטלו
ועודן עליו, metaltelo v'odan alav, you do not have to shake it
off because there you have there is no other option, so therefore
you move the whole thing. וכן תני חייא בר רב מדפתי, V'chen
tani Chiya bar Rav mi-Difeti, so we taught similarly in a ברייתא,
לא שנו אלא לצורך גופו, that's only when you need the pillow
so we don't allow you to keep on moving the money. אבל
לצורך מקומו, if you need to get everything out of the way,
מטלטלו ועודן עליו, you can move it again, you're not directly moving
the money, you're moving the pillow with the money, and because you
don't have another option that is allowed. So the עמוד ב' Amud
Bet here very much reinforces everything we said on the עמוד א'.
Amud Aleph. מאי שנא מנוער, Mai shena m'noer,
so again this point about shaking it off. Okay, אמר רבי אושעיא,
Amar Rabbi Oshaya, שכח ארנקי בחצר, shachach arnaki b'chatzer,
if you forgot your wallet in the courtyard, מניח עליה כיכר או
תינוק ומטלטלה, meniach aleha kikar o tinok u'metaltela, you can, and so
you don't want to leave your court, now it's in the courtyard,
which means there's not a carrying problem but there's a מוקצה muktzeh
problem. So you don't want to leave your wallet there in the
middle of the courtyard, so you put a loaf of bread on
it or an infant on it and then you carry it. Now
why is that different than our case of the barrel with the
stone on it or or the pillow with the money?
What am I fundamentally moving? If I put a a piece of
bread on top of my wallet, I'm going to pick up my
directly my wallet. A, the thing I am physically handling directly is
the מוקצה, muktzeh and B, the fundamental purpose of moving it is
the מוקצה. muktzeh Right, our משנה was better for two reasons. The
fundamental thing I'm handling is the היתר heter and the fundamental interest
is the דבר המותר. davar hamutar. Okay, so but he says that
actually in this case because there's a concern of הפסד ממון, hefsed
mamon, loss of money, we allow you to do this.
Seems only for an ארנקי. arnaki.
Well, one minute. That's what you would think. Let's see where the
גמרא Gemara goes. אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, שכח לבינה בחצר,
shachach levana b'chatzer,
let's say you forgot like a brick in the courtyard, מניח עליה
כיכר או תינוק ומטלטלה. meniach aleha kikar o tinok u'metaltela. So he's
basically making exactly that point. It doesn't have to be a wallet,
doesn't have to be a lot of money. Even anything you don't
want damaged we allow you to do this trick. So here's a
perfect trick of moving מוקצה, muktzeh put some non-מוקצה muktzeh on top
of it. Okay, which is wild. אמר רב יהודה בר שילא, Amar
Rav Yehuda bar Shila, don't worry, we're not going to end that
way. אמר רב יהודה בר שילא אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Yehuda
bar Shila amar Rav Assi, פעם אחת שכחו דסקיא מלאה מעות באיסטרטיא,
paam achat shachechu daskia meleah maot b'istatya, once they left a sack
filled with money in a רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. So now besides
the מוקצה muktzeh issue we've got a carrying issue. All right, everyone
knows the Chassidic story. Shabbos, okay, I didn't know, okay, I'll start
anyway.
ובאו ושאלו את רבי יוחנן, u-bau v'shaalu et Rabbi Yochanan, so they
asked Rabbi Yochanan, ואמר להם, v'amar lahem, הניחו עליה כיכר או תינוק,
henichu aleha kikar o tinok, put a loaf of bread or infant.
Now where do you get a loaf of bread in the middle
of the רשות הרבים? reshut harabbim? Okay, so maybe anyway let's say
an infant, whatever. And so A, that solves the מוקצה muktzeh, problem,
but how are you going to carry it? בטלטול b'tiltul and move
it. So what do you mean move it? Where are you going
to move it? So רש"י Rashi says well we mean like little
gradations, פחות פחות מארבע אמות. pachot pachot m'arba amot. So A, we're
allowing carrying by doing each separate act as just as less than
the minimum amount, and B, we're allowing we're allowing this moving of
מוקצה muktzeh, through this way. Okay, now we are going to see
in a coming up משנה that when you're caught outside of the
city with your money on you they allow you to do tricks
to carry it, without exactly violating, because they know that if we
don't allow you to do those things you're going to come to
carry it directly and violate שבת. Shabbat. So we allow a lot
of a lot of ways to do it that really is very,
that really come close to the edge. Okay, fine, but here we're
throwing in in addition to all of that the idea of the
מוקצה muktzeh, issue. Okay, that you can even that you can get
around מוקצה muktzeh. problems as well.
So the לבינה levana is also since it's I guess very, very
valuable?
I don't think so. I think his לבינה levana point is even
if it's not so valuable. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara, says like
this, so that's what we're saying so far besides the idea about
dealing with carrying which is דאורייתא, d'Oraita, it's also saying that you
can use a trick to deal with the מוקצה muktzeh. when you're
afraid of the thing will get damaged. You have to note the
irony of course because a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, kli she'melachto l'issur the
one thing you cannot move a כלי kli, שמלאכתו לאיסור for is
what? מחמה לצל, me-chama l'tzel, if you're trying to protect it from
damage. And here you have something that's real מוקצה muktzeh, and you're
allowed to do a trick as a way to move it. But
again, we're not going to end this way.
So basically what we're saying so far though if I want to
put something on my hammer, then that'd be allowed right?
Correct. Okay, but if you're afraid it's going to get damaged. But
we're not ending that way. So let's take a look. אמר מר
זוטרא, Amar Mar Zutra, הלכתא ככל הני שמעתתא בשוכח. hilchata k'chol hanei
shematata b'shocheach.
We rule like all of this if you forgot your wallet or
whatever because but if you intentionally left it there, we're not going
to give you this allowance if you intentionally left the thing in
the middle of the street before שבת Shabbat or in the middle
of the courtyard. רב אשי אמר אפילו שכח נמי לא. Rav Ashi
amar afilu shachach nami lo. I'm sorry, even if you forgot it
there I'm not we're not going to allow this stuff, forget everything
we just said. ולא אמרו כיכר או תינוק אלא למת בלבד. v'lo
amru kikar o tinok ela l'met bilvad. The one place we find
in earlier Rabbinic literature that they allowed this is in a case
of a dead body. So if it's a dead body and respect
for the dead and you have to move it in a way
that it won't that
it'll move it out of the sun in some way of to
get to move it to to protect the to protect it from
from spoiling from becoming
decomposing, so then they allowed it by doing this but fundamentally this
never allowed. But fundamentally this never applied elsewhere. It didn't apply to
הפסד hefsed didn't apply anything else. And that's basically the way we
rule. Okay. So this is the flipping of our משנה. Again the
מוקצה muktzeh. is on bottom, the היתר is on top, you're handling
the מוקצה, muktzeh you're doing it for the sake of the מוקצה,
muktzeh so the גמרא Gemara thinks that the first to thinks assumption
was maybe they're fine, but maybe you can still do it when
there's a concern of הפסד. hefsed. And the answer is no. That
was a very special trick that we only allowed by מת meis
and we do not allow it anywhere else. Yeah, you have to
put the כיכר kikar on it.
Is the ruling that way because רב אשי Rav Ashi is the
later authority than all these other authorities here?
Could be. I mean that normally is, you know, we'll see the
גמרא Gemara isn't done yet either, but yes, certainly רב אשי Rav
Ashi very often has the last word. So let's take a look.
אביי, Abaye, because we're going to see that אביי Abaye and רבא
Rava did not agree to רב אשי. Rav Ashi.
And they were earlier.
Yeah, they were earlier, but they're pretty big authorities. אביי מנח כפא
אכיפי. Abaye manach kafa akifi. So אביי Abaye would put a... but
we'll see what the גמרא Gemara does with it. Okay. אביי Abaye
would put some type of a ladle on like a bundle of
wheat and therefore and then carry the bundle of wheat. Sounding like
again not a big הפסד, hefsed, sounding like the same approach. רבא
מנח סכינא אבר יונה ומטלטלה. Rava manach sakina abar yona umataltela. רבא
Rava would put a knife on top of a pigeon, a שחוטה
shechted pigeon and carry it. Again, presumably the שחוטה shechted pigeon which
isn't cooked and it's raw and whatever is מוקצה, muktzeh. and but
he would put a knife on it and carry it to prevent
loss, seeming again seeming that this is okay even not in the
case of a מת. meis. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, so
said רב יוסף Rav Yosef who was their רבי, כמה חריפא שמעתתא
דדרדקי. kama charifa shma'atecha d'dardaki. How sharp, he said this, he said
this mockingly. Oh look look at how smart these young kids are.
Now they weren't kids, but the point is they were kids vis-a-vis
him. They were his students, they were younger, whatever. So he said,
ah yeah, these young'uns are really think that they're so smart. Okay,
like אימא דאמרי רבנן, eima d'amri Rabbanan, when did the Rabbis say
that you can do this trick? בשוכח, b'shochei'ach, if you forgot it.
Now notice he's not limiting it to a מת. meis. רב יוסף
Rav Yosef is saying it's okay to do it, but only when
the thing was forgotten. לכתחילה מי אמרי, l'chatchila mi amri, did they
say it לכתחילה? l'chatchila? And here you knew that you were leaving
your bundle of wheat out before שבת Shabbos began or the pigeon
out. So his concern is not that we only apply it to
a מת, meis, but that this is not a case of בשוכח.
b'shochei'ach. It's a case of מניח. meiniach. So let's see what they
said back. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back, one
minute. אי לאו דאדם חשוב אנא, ilav d'adam chashuv ana, if I
were not an אדם חשוב, adam chashuv, by the way, that's probably
playing off the fact that רב יוסף Rav Yosef just called him
a kid. Okay, so if it were not that I were an
אדם חשוב, adam chashuv, כפא אכיפי למה לי, kafa kefi lama li,
I wouldn't even have to put the ladle on the bundles. The
bundles are not really מוקצה. muktzeh So I'm just doing it so
people don't get mistaken, but it's really not even necessary. Why? דחזי
למזגא איי, d'chazu l'mizga ai, you can recline on these bundles of
wheat, which is pretty funny. So what if you can recline? Like
you can use a stone as a doorstep, it doesn't make it
not מוקצה. muktzeh So anyway, but that's what אביי Abaye said. Maybe
it was common to recline on it, I don't know. It wasn't
really מוקצה, muktzeh so that's why I was allowed to do it.
And I only bothered doing it because I'm an אדם חשוב. adam
chashuv. אמר רבא, Rava רבא Rava, said, אנא אי
לאו דאדם חשוב אנא, ana ilav d'adam chashuv ana, again רבא, Rava
same point, don't call me a kid. אנא סכינא אבר יונה למה
לי, ana sakina abar yona lama li, I wouldn't have to put
the knife on the pigeon. The pigeon really isn't מוקצה. muktzeh. דחזי
לאומצא, d'chazi l'umtza, you can eat the pigeon raw, some people eat
the pigeon raw and therefore it's not מוקצה muktzeh. and therefore it's
not a problem. So in the end discussion of the גמרא Gemara
after the רב אשי, Rav Ashi, after רב אשי Rav Ashi said
none of this applies, going back to sort of Charlie's point, the
final voice in this discussion is רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, אביי, Abaye,
and רבא Rava that all basically say fundamentally you are allowed to
do it in a case of בשוכח b'shochei'ach when you forgot. The
only limitation is not מניח. Don't worry though, we don't פוסקים pasken
that way. Okay.
רב אשי Rav Ashi edited the משנה, and גמרא Gemara I mean,
and then he wrote it, and then who wrote this...
First of all, just because you edited it doesn't mean you write
your own version last, but anyway, I'm not going to get into
who really edited the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, let's just read a little bit more about this
pigeon, see if we get up to the next משנה. טעמא דחזי
לאומצא, ta'ama d'chazi l'umtza,
one minute, says the גמרא, the reason you're saying the pigeon isn't
מוקצה muktzeh is because you could eat it raw. הא לא חזי
לאומצא לא, ha lo chazi l'umtza lo, if it wasn't able to
be eaten raw, no, it would be considered מוקצה. muktzeh Why is
that? You could give it to your dog. So it shouldn't be
מוקצה Muktzah. just if it's fit for animal eating. So לימא דרבא
כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה, leima d'Rava k'Rabbi Yehuda svira lei, it must
be that רבא Rava holds like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda, is basically the position that is contrasted to רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, holds of מוקצה Muktzah. or certainly a much more מוקצה
Muktzah. than רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does. And here, it were only...
the point about the pigeon is the following. Dog food is not
מוקצה. Muktzah. But the pigeon is something that when you you want
to eat it for yourself. You want to cook it. But right
now on שבת, Shabbos, so it's fundamentally set aside for מאכל אדם.
ma'achal adam. But right now on שבת Shabbos that it's raw, it's
only fit for dog food, if that were the case, if people
didn't eat it raw. So therefore, according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
that would be מוקצה. Muktzah, Something that is intended for מאכל אדם
ma'achal adam that right but can't be eaten by people right now
and can only be eaten by dogs, that is considered
מוקצה Muktzah, because you still want to use it for מאכל אדם.
ma'achal adam. Okay, so that's considered מוקצה because and it's not fit...
from מאכל אדם. Ma'achal Adam. So the גמרא says one minute, so
והא, ve-ha, that sounds like that's what רבא's Rava saying, or else
he could have just said you could feed it to the dogs.
ואמר רבא לשמעיה, Ve-amar Rava li-shmayei, רבא Rava said to his attendants,
תבי לי בר אווזא, tavi li bar avza, roast for me a
duck, בר אווזא bar avza is a duck, yeah, a duck, roast
for me a duck, this was on יום טוב, Yom Tov, not
שבת, Shabbos, ושדי מאיה לשונרא, ve-shadi maya li-shunra, and throw the intestines,
the guts to the cat. Okay now, why could you throw the
guts to the cat? The גמרא assumes that the guts could have
been eaten by humans as well, you know, so sweetbreads I guess
or whatever, I don't know, anyway, chitlins, anyway, so and by throwing
it to the cat he's basically sort of treating it as מאכל
בהמה, Ma'achal Behema, something that really could have been מאכל אדם, Ma'achal
Adam, and that should have made it מוקצה. Now it's a little
strange because it's not so clear what the question is. The assumption
being that since this is in theory fit for מאכל אדם, Ma'achal
Adam, okay, if you're only willing to sort of, you know, use
it for מאכל בהמה, Ma'achal Behema, that should be מוקצה. Okay, so
the גמרא says התם, hasam, no, כיון דמסרח דעתו עלויה מאתמול, kivan
di-masrach daito alavei mei-etmol, there, so there, it's not fit for מאכל
אדם. Ma'achal Adam. If you were to leave the intestines for later,
you know, apparently they had, I don't know, do some process with
it to get the guck out of it, so you could have
eaten it after יום טוב Yom Tov but not on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. Okay, so there, were you to have waited for it,
it would have spoiled, so therefore from the very beginning when they
came into יום טוב Yom Tov with this duck, they knew that
they were going to use the meat for the people and the
intestines for the cat. So the assumption is, if you had planned
initially for the whole duck to be for people and now it's
only usable for the cat or for dog food, that should be
מוקצה. Because if מאכל אדם Ma'achal Adam is not, if it's only
usable for מאכל בהמה, Ma'achal Behema, something that was designated as מאכל
אדם, Ma'achal Adam, then that would be considered מוקצה. And the גמרא
says no, the intestines were never designated as מאכל אדם, Ma'achal Adam,
you always knew that you were going to give them to the
cat. So the גמרא says הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistavra, that
also makes sense, דרבא כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה, de-Rava ke-Rabbi Yehuda sevira
lei, רבא Rava will hold like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda. דדרש רבא,
de-darash Rava, רבא Rava expounded, אשה לא תיכנס לבית העצים ליטול מהן
אוד, isha lo tikanes le-veis ha-eitzim litol me-hen ud, a woman cannot
go in to the like shed of wood, the woodshed, to take
a like a poker, an אוד, ud, ואוד שנשבר אסור להסיקו ביום
טוב, ve-ud she-nishbar asur le-hasiko be-Yom Tov, and similarly or like a
spit, and a poker or spit that breaks, you can't, you can't
fix it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Again, this is יום טוב,
Yom Tov, so you could use the wood for what do you
call it, you could use the wood for firewood, but not to
make it into a כלי, and if it breaks you can't fix
it. Now, לפי, lefi, now why can't you just, why, now I'm
sorry, not להסיקו, le-hasiko, I'm sorry, if it breaks you cannot use
it as firewood, ואוד שנשבר אסור להסיקו ביום טוב, ve-ud she-nishbar asur
le-hasiko be-Yom Tov, if it breaks you can't use it as firewood.
So that's what we're going to focus on. לפי שמסיקין בכילים, lefi
she-masikin be-keilim,
because you can
use as firewood whole vessels, ואין מסיקין בשברי כילים, ve-ein masikin be-shivrei
keilim, not broken vessels. Why? That's what you want to use as
firewood, but because that's נולד. nolad. Okay, so you see רבא holds
of נולד, nolad, so you see שמע מינה, shma mina, he holds
like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda It's again another very strange גמרא. Just
because he holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, about נולד nolad doesn't
necessarily mean that he holds of this issue about מאכל אדם, Ma'achal
Adam, מאכל בהמה. Ma'achal Behema. But the גמרא seems to sort of,
you know, sort of put all the things in the same package.
So since רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda so since he holds of רבי
יהודה of נולד, nolad, if he had just said that this pigeon
was fit for the dogs, it would still have been מוקצה, because
since you want it for מאכל אדם, Ma'achal Adam, if it's only
usable for מאכל בהמה, Ma'achal Behema, that's מוקצה, and therefore he had
to say that it is usable for מאכל אדם Ma'achal Adam because
you would be prepared to eat it raw.